Finding Aid for Arthur W. Haydon diaries, 1865-1879 and 1888-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur W. Haydon diaries 1865-1879 and 1888-1915
Haydon, Arthur W., 1844-1918.
1.5 linear feet (34 volumes and 1 folder)
851436 Aa 2
Student at the University of Michigan, 1865-1867, later Decatur, Michigan, sheep breeder. Diaries describing student life at the University of Michigan, 1865-1867; later diaries include brief comments on weather and mundane daily events and activities; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. and Mrs. Erwin Ruff (donor no. 3929 ) and was received July 10, 1962.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Arthur Williams Haydon was born on April 22, 1844 in Hamilton Township, Van Buren County. His parents, Philotas and Adelaide Broughton Haydon, came to Michigan from Vermont in 1837. Haydon spent all of his life in the Hamilton community except for a few years at school in Kalamazoo and Ann Arbor. He attended the University of Michigan but did not graduate. He married his school sweetheart, Mary E. Baker, on October 19, 1868. They had two children, both girls. Haydon was known throughout the state of Michigan as a breeder of fine horses and sheep. He built his own farm which came to be known as "Shady Knoll" for the trees he planted which grew to such large proportions. He died on August 8, 1918.
The Arthur W. Haydon collection consists almost exclusively of diaries kept by Arthur from 1865 to 1878 and 1888 to 1915. The diaries are simply collections of Arthur's thoughts. The earliest entries are more fulsome than those for his later life.
Of particular interest are the two volumes, 1865-1866 and 1866-1878. The first of these was written while Arthur was away at school in Ann Arbor. He attended the University of Michigan for two years, 1865/66 and 1866/67. The entries show Arthur's love of school. Not only does he describe his days with great detail and emotion, but the style in which they are written reveals a young man who truly enjoys life. There are no diaries for the years 1879-1887. After 1878 there is a volume for each. The prose becomes much simpler. Haydon describes the weather for the day, the chores he performed, and the everyday events of his life, Only occasionally are the diary entries for these years revealing of Haydon's thoughts and emotions.
In addition to the diaries there is a folder containing miscellaneous newspaper clippings he saved about events important to him as well as a few family mementos. The photographs are of his house and farm buildings.
Subjects:
Agriculture.; Decatur (Mich.); Haydon, Arthur W., 1844-1918.; Horse breeders.; Sheep.; University of Michigan--Students--1861-1870.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Barns--Michigan--Hamilton (Van Buren County: Township); Construction.; Dwellings--Michigan--Hamilton (Van Buren County: Township); Hamilton (Van Buren County, Mich.: Township)--Barns.; Hamilton (Van Buren County, Mich.: Township)--Dwellings.; Haydon, Arthur W., 1844-1918.
Genre Terms:
Ambrotypes.; Cyanotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.
- Diaries
  - 1864-1867 (Box 1)
  - 1865-1866 (Box 1)
  - 1866-1878 (Box 1)
  - 1879, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891 (Box 1)
  - 1892 (Box 1)
  - 1893 (Box 1)
  - 1894 (Box 1)
  - 1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896 (Box 1)
  - 1897 (Box 1)
  - 1898 (Box 1)
  - 1899 (Box 1)
  - 1900 (Box 1)
  - 1901 (Box 1)
  - 1902 (Box 1)
  - 1903 (Box 1)
  - 1904 (Box 1)
  - 1905 (Box 1)
  - 1906 (Box 1)
  - 1907 (Box 1)
  - 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 2)
  - 1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1915 (Box 2)
- Other materials
  - Miscellaneous (newspaper clippings, personal letters, graduation invitations, etc.) (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Haydon's house and farm buildings and barn construction (Box 2)
    (see also unidentified ambrotype portrait in UAx files)